<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
	<string
		name="history">
<![CDATA[
<p>NetHack History file for release 3.6</p>

<p>Behold, mortal, the origins of NetHack...</p>

<p>Jay Fenlason wrote the original Hack with help from Kenny Woodland,<br/>
Mike Thome, and Jon Payne.</p>

<p>Andries Brouwer did a major re-write, transforming Hack into a very different<br/>
game, and published (at least) three versions (1.0.1, 1.0.2, and 1.0.3) for<br/>
UNIX(tm) machines to the Usenet.</p>

<p>Don G. Kneller ported Hack 1.0.3 to Microsoft(tm) C and MS-DOS(tm), producing<br/>
PC HACK 1.01e, added support for DEC Rainbow graphics in version 1.03g, and<br/>
went on to produce at least four more versions (3.0, 3.2, 3.51, and 3.6;<br/>
note that these are old Hack version numbers, not contemporary NetHack ones).</p>

<p>R. Black ported PC HACK 3.51 to Lattice(tm) C and the Atari 520/1040ST,<br/>
producing ST Hack 1.03.</p>

<p>Mike Stephenson merged these various versions back together, incorporating<br/>
many of the added features, and produced NetHack version 1.4 in 1987.  He<br/>
then coordinated a cast of thousands in enhancing and debugging NetHack 1.4<br/>
and released NetHack versions 2.2 and 2.3.</p>

<p>Later, Mike coordinated a major rewrite of the game, heading a team which<br/>
included Ken Arromdee, Jean-Christophe Collet, Steve Creps, Eric Hendrickson,<br/>
Izchak Miller, Eric S. Raymond, John Rupley, Mike Threepoint, and Janet Walz,<br/>
to produce NetHack 3.0c.  The same group subsequently released ten patch-<br/>
level revisions and updates of 3.0.</p>

<p>NetHack 3.0 was ported to the Atari by Eric R. Smith, to OS/2 by Timo<br/>
Hakulinen, and to VMS by David Gentzel.  The three of them and Kevin Darcy<br/>
later joined the main development team to produce subsequent revisions of<br/>
3.0.</p>

<p>Olaf Seibert ported NetHack 2.3 and 3.0 to the Amiga.  Norm Meluch, Stephen<br/>
Spackman and Pierre Martineau designed overlay code for PC NetHack 3.0.<br/>
Johnny Lee ported NetHack 3.0 to the Macintosh.  Along with various other<br/>
Dungeoneers, they continued to enhance the PC, Macintosh, and Amiga ports<br/>
through the later revisions of 3.0.</p>

<p>Headed by Mike Stephenson and coordinated by Izchak Miller and Janet Walz,<br/>
the development team which now included Ken Arromdee, David Cohrs,<br/>
Jean-Christophe Collet, Kevin Darcy, Matt Day, Timo Hakulinen, Steve Linhart,<br/>
Dean Luick, Pat Rankin, Eric Raymond, and Eric Smith undertook a radical<br/>
revision of 3.0.  They re-structured the game\'s design, and re-wrote major<br/>
parts of the code.  They added multiple dungeons, a new display, special<br/>
individual character quests, a new endgame and many other new features, and<br/>
produced NetHack 3.1.</p>

<p>Ken Lorber, Gregg Wonderly and Greg Olson, with help from Richard Addison,<br/>
Mike Passaretti, and Olaf Seibert, developed NetHack 3.1 for the Amiga.</p>

<p>Norm Meluch and Kevin Smolkowski, with help from Carl Schelin, Stephen<br/>
Spackman, Steve VanDevender, and Paul Winner, ported NetHack 3.1 to the PC.</p>

<p>Jon W{tte and Hao-yang Wang, with help from Ross Brown, Mike Engber, David<br/>
Hairston, Michael Hamel, Jonathan Handler, Johnny Lee, Tim Lennan, Rob Menke,<br/>
and Andy Swanson developed NetHack 3.1 for the Macintosh, porting it for<br/>
MPW.  Building on their development, Barton House added a Think C port.</p>

<p>Timo Hakulinen ported NetHack 3.1 to OS/2.  Eric Smith ported NetHack 3.1<br/>
to the Atari.  Pat Rankin, with help from Joshua Delahunty, is responsible<br/>
for the VMS version of NetHack 3.1.  Michael Allison ported NetHack 3.1 to<br/>
Windows NT.</p>

<p>Dean Luick, with help from David Cohrs, developed NetHack 3.1 for X11.<br/>
Warwick Allison wrote a tiled version of NetHack for the Atari;<br/>
he later contributed the tiles to the DevTeam and tile support was<br/>
then added to other platforms.</p>

<p>The 3.2 development team, comprised of Michael Allison, Ken Arromdee, David<br/>
Cohrs, Jessie Collet, Steve Creps, Kevin Darcy, Timo Hakulinen, Steve<br/>
Linhart, Dean Luick, Pat Rankin, Eric Smith, Mike Stephenson, Janet Walz, and<br/>
Paul Winner, released version 3.2 in April of 1996.</p>

<p>Version 3.2 marked the tenth anniversary of the formation of the development<br/>
team.  In a testament to their dedication to the game, all thirteen members<br/>
of the original development team remained on the team at the start of work<br/>
on that release.  During the interval between the release of 3.1.3 and 3.2,<br/>
one of the founding members of the development team, Dr. Izchak Miller,<br/>
passed away.  That release of the game was dedicated to him by the<br/>
development and porting teams.</p>

<p>Version 3.2 proved to be more stable than previous versions.  Many bugs<br/>
were fixed, abuses eliminated, and game features tuned for better game<br/>
play.</p>

<p>During the lifespan of NetHack 3.1 and 3.2, several enthusiasts of the game<br/>
added their own modifications to the game and made these "variants" publicly<br/>
available:</p>

<p>Tom Proudfoot and Yuval Oren created NetHack++, which was quickly renamed<br/>
NetHack--.  Working independently, Stephen White wrote NetHack Plus.<br/>
Tom Proudfoot later merged NetHack Plus and his own NetHack-- to produce<br/>
SLASH.  Larry Stewart-Zerba and Warwick Allison improved the spellcasting<br/>
system with the Wizard Patch.  Warwick Allison also ported NetHack to use<br/>
the Qt interface.</p>

<p>Warren Cheung combined SLASH with the Wizard Patch to produce Slash\'em, and<br/>
with the help of Kevin Hugo, added more features.  Kevin later joined the<br/>
DevTeam and incorporated the best of these ideas in NetHack 3.3.</p>

<p>The final update to 3.2 was the bug fix release 3.2.3, which was released<br/>
simultaneously with 3.3.0 in December 1999 just in time for the Year 2000.</p>

<p>The 3.3 development team, consisting of Michael Allison, Ken Arromdee,<br/>
David Cohrs, Jessie Collet, Steve Creps, Kevin Darcy, Timo Hakulinen,<br/>
Kevin Hugo, Steve Linhart, Ken Lorber, Dean Luick, Pat Rankin, Eric Smith,<br/>
Mike Stephenson, Janet Walz, and Paul Winner, released 3.3.0 in<br/>
December 1999 and 3.3.1 in August of 2000.</p>

<p>Version 3.3 offered many firsts. It was the first version to separate race<br/>
and profession. The Elf class was removed in preference to an elf race,<br/>
and the races of dwarves, gnomes, and orcs made their first appearance in<br/>
the game alongside the familiar human race.  Monk and Ranger roles joined<br/>
Archeologists, Barbarians, Cavemen, Healers, Knights, Priests, Rogues,<br/>
Samurai, Tourists, Valkyries and of course, Wizards.  It was also the first<br/>
version to allow you to ride a steed, and was the first version to have a<br/>
publicly available web-site listing all the bugs that had been discovered.<br/>
Despite that constantly growing bug list, 3.3 proved stable enough to last<br/>
for more than a year and a half.</p>

<p>The 3.4 development team initially consisted of Michael Allison, Ken Arromdee,<br/>
David Cohrs, Jessie Collet, Kevin Hugo, Ken Lorber, Dean Luick, Pat Rankin,<br/>
Mike Stephenson, Janet Walz, and Paul Winner, with Warwick Allison joining<br/>
just before the release of NetHack 3.4.0 in March 2002.</p>

<p>As with version 3.3, various people contributed to the game as a whole as<br/>
well as supporting ports on the different platforms that NetHack runs on:</p>

<p>Pat Rankin maintained 3.4 for VMS.</p>

<p>Michael Allison maintained NetHack 3.4 for the MS-DOS platform.<br/>
Paul Winner and Yitzhak Sapir provided encouragement.</p>

<p>Dean Luick, Mark Modrall, and Kevin Hugo maintained and enhanced the<br/>
Macintosh port of 3.4.</p>

<p>Michael Allison, David Cohrs, Alex Kompel, Dion Nicolaas, and Yitzhak Sapir<br/>
maintained and enhanced 3.4 for the Microsoft Windows platform.  Alex Kompel<br/>
contributed a new graphical interface for the Windows port.  Alex Kompel also<br/>
contributed a Windows CE port for 3.4.1.</p>

<p>Ron Van Iwaarden maintained 3.4 for OS/2.</p>

<p>Janne Salmijarvi and Teemu Suikki maintained and enhanced the<br/>
Amiga port of 3.5 after Janne Salmijarvi resurrected it for 3.3.1.</p>

<p>Christian `Marvin\' Bressler maintained 3.5 for the Atari after he<br/>
resurrected it for 3.3.1.</p>

<p>The release of NetHack 3.4.3 in December 2003 marked the beginning of a<br/>
long release hiatus.  3.4.3 proved to be a remarkably stable version that<br/>
provided continued enjoyment by the community for more than a decade.  The<br/>
devteam slowly and quietly continued to work on the game behind the scenes<br/>
during the tenure of 3.4.3.  It was during that same period that several<br/>
new variants emerged within the NetHack community.  Notably sporkhack by<br/>
Derek S. Ray, unnethack by Patric Mueller, nitrohack and its successors<br/>
originally by Daniel Thaler and then by Alex Smith, and<br/>
Dynahack by Tung Nguyen.  Some of those variants continue to be developed,<br/>
maintained, and enjoyed by the community to this day.</p>

<p>In September 2014, an interim snapshot of the code under development was<br/>
released publicly by other parties.  Since that code was a work-in-progress<br/>
and had not gone through a period of debugging, it was decided that the<br/>
version numbers present on that code snapshot would be retired and never<br/>
used in an official NetHack release.  An announcement was posted on the<br/>
devteam\'s official nethack.org website to that effect, stating that there<br/>
would never be a 3.4.4, 3.5, or 3.5.0 official release version.</p>

<p>In January 2015, preparation began for the release of NetHack 3.6.</p>

<p>At the beginning of development for what would eventually get released<br/>
as 3.6.0, the development team consisted of Michael Allison,<br/>
Warwick Allison, Ken Arromdee, David Cohrs, Jessie Collet, Ken Lorber,<br/>
Dean Luick, Pat Rankin, Mike Stephenson, Janet Walz, and Paul Winner.<br/>
Leading up to the release of 3.6.0 in early 2015, new members Sean Hunt,<br/>
Pasi Kallinen, and Derek S. Ray joined the NetHack development team.</p>

<p>In January 2015, preparation began for the release of NetHack 3.6.  The 3.6<br/>
version merges work done by the development team since the previous release<br/>
with some of the beloved community patches.  Many bugs were fixed and some<br/>
code was restructured.</p>

<p>The development team, as well as Steve VanDevender and Kevin Smolkowski<br/>
ensured that NetHack 3.6.0 continued to operate on various Unix flavors<br/>
as well as maintaining the X11 interface.</p>

<p>Ken Lorber, Haoyang Wang, Pat Rankin, and Dean Luick maintained the port<br/>
of NetHack 3.6.0 for Mac.</p>

<p>Michael Allison, Derek S. Ray, Yitzhak Sapir, Alex Kompel, Dion Nicolaas,<br/>
and David Cohrs maintained the port of NetHack 3.6.0 for Microsoft Windows.</p>

<p>Pat Rankin attempted to keep the VMS port running for NetHack 3.6.0,<br/>
hindered by limited access.  Kevin Smolkowski has updated and tested it<br/>
for the most recent version of OpenVMS (V8.4 as of this writing) on Alpha<br/>
and Integrity (aka Itanium aka IA64) but not VAX.</p>

<p>This version of the game is special in a particular way.  Near the end of<br/>
the development of 3.6, one of the significant inspirations for many of<br/>
the humorous and fun features found in the game, author Terry Pratchett,<br/>
passed away.  This version of the game includes a tribute to him.</p>


<p>An official NetHack web site continues to be maintained by Ken Lorber at<br/>
http://www.nethack.org/.</p>

<p>--
SHOUT-OUTS</p>

<p>The devteam would like to give a special "shout-out" to thank the generous<br/>
people primarily responsible for the public NetHack servers available for<br/>
playing the game at nethack.alt.org and devnull.net.  In addition to<br/>
providing a way for the public to play a game of NetHack from almost<br/>
anywhere, they have hosted annual NetHack tournaments for many, many years.</p>

<p>On behalf of the NetHack community, thank you very much to<br/>
M. Drew Streib, Pasi Kallinen and Robin Bandy.</p>

<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;- - - - - - - - - -</p>

<p>From time to time, some depraved individual out there in netland sends a<br/>
particularly intriguing modification to help out with the game.  The Gods of<br/>
the Dungeon sometimes make note of the names of the worst of these miscreants<br/>
in this, the list of Dungeoneers:</p>

Adam Aronow&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Janet Walz&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Nathan Eady<br/>
Alex Kompel&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Janne Salmijarvi&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Norm Meluch<br/>
Andreas Dorn&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Jean-Christophe Collet&nbsp;&nbsp;Olaf Seibert<br/>
Andy Church&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Jeff Bailey&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Pasi Kallinen<br/>
Andy Swanson&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Jochen Erwied&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Pat Rankin<br/>
Ari Huttunen&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;John Kallen&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Paul Winner<br/>
Barton House&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;John Rupley&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Pierre Martineau<br/>
Benson I. Margulies&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;John S. Bien&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Ralf Brown<br/>
Bill Dyer&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Johnny Lee&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Ray Chason<br/>
Boudewijn Waijers&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Jon W{tte&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Richard Addison<br/>
Bruce Cox&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Jonathan Handler&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Richard Beigel<br/>
Bruce Holloway&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Joshua Delahunty&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Richard P. Hughey<br/>
Bruce Mewborne&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Keizo Yamamoto&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Rob Menke<br/>
Carl Schelin&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Ken Arnold&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Robin Bandy<br/>
Chris Russo&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Ken Arromdee&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Robin Johnson<br/>
David Cohrs&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Ken Lorber&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Roderick Schertler<br/>
David Damerell&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Ken Washikita&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Roland McGrath<br/>
David Gentzel&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Kevin Darcy&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Ron Van Iwaarden<br/>
David Hairston&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Kevin Hugo&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Ronnen Miller<br/>
Dean Luick&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Kevin Sitze&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Ross Brown<br/>
Del Lamb&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Kevin Smolkowski&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Sascha Wostmann<br/>
Derek S. Ray&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Kevin Sweet&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Scott Bigham<br/>
Deron Meranda&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Lars Huttar&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Scott R. Turner<br/>
Dion Nicolaas&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Leon Arnott&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Sean Hunt<br/>
Dylan O\'Donnell&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;M. Drew Streib&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Stephen Spackman<br/>
Eric Backus&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Malcolm Ryan&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Stefan Thielscher<br/>
Eric Hendrickson&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Mark Gooderum&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Stephen White<br/>
Eric R. Smith&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Mark Modrall&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Steve Creps<br/>
Eric S. Raymond&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Marvin Bressler&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Steve Linhart<br/>
Erik Andersen&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Matthew Day&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Steve VanDevender<br/>
Frederick Roeber&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Merlyn LeRoy&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Teemu Suikki<br/>
Gil Neiger&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Michael Allison&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Tim Lennan<br/>
Greg Laskin&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Michael Feir&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Timo Hakulinen<br/>
Greg Olson&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Michael Hamel&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Tom Almy<br/>
Gregg Wonderly&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Michael Sokolov&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Tom West<br/>
Hao-yang Wang&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Mike Engber&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Warren Cheung<br/>
Helge Hafting&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Mike Gallop&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Warwick Allison<br/>
Irina Rempt-Drijfhout&nbsp;&nbsp;Mike Passaretti&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Yitzhak Sapir<br/>
Izchak Miller&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Mike Stephenson<br/>
J. Ali Harlow&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Mikko Juola<br/>
]]>
	</string>
	<string
		name="credits">
<![CDATA[

<p><h1>NetHack Android Port</h1><br/>
Based on NetHack 3.6.0<br/>
<a href="http://www.nethack.org">http://www.nethack.org</a></p>
<p><small>Inspired by NetHack iPhone Port by <a href="http://code.google.com/p/iNetHack/">Dirk Zimmermann</a></small></p>

<p><br/><br/><h2>Hearse Implementation</h2>
<i>by Ranbato</i><br/>
<a href="https://github.com/Ranbato">https://github.com/Ranbato</a></p>

<p><br/><br/><h2>The Absurd NetHack Tileset</h2>
<i>by John Shaw</i><br/>
<a href="http://www.thinktwicenews.com">www.thinktwicenews.com</a><br/>
Modified by gurr</p>

<p><br/><br/><h2>Chozo Tiles</h2>
<i>by James Hogwood</i><br/>
<a href="http://www.multifoliate.com/nh/">http://www.multifoliate.com/nh</a><br/>
Modified by Patric Mueller and gurr</p>

<p><br/><br/><h2>DragonDePlatino\'s tileset</h2>
<i>by Andrew Rios</i><br/>
<a href="http://dragondeplatino.daportfolio.com/about/">http://dragondeplatino.daportfolio.com/about/</a></p><br/>
Modified by gurr</p>

<p><br/><br/><h2>Geoduck\'s tileset</h2>
<i>by Robert M. Cook</i><br/>
<a href="http://cook.web.eschelon.com/nhack.html">http://cook.web.eschelon.com/nhack.html</a></p>

<p><br/><br/><h2>Nevanda Tiles</h2>
<i>by Nevanda</i><br/>
<a href="http://nevanda.deviantart.com/art/nethack-tiles-32x32px-416691316">http://nevanda.deviantart.com/art/nethack-tiles-32x32px-416691316</a><br/>
Modified by Brendan Dwyer</p>

<p><br/><small>&copy; 2015 Martin Gustafsson</small></p>
]]>
	</string>
	<string
		name="license">
<![CDATA[
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;NetHack GENERAL PUBLIC LICENSE<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;(Copyright 1989 M. Stephenson)<br/>
<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;(Based on the BISON general public license,<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;copyright 1988 Richard M. Stallman)<br/>
<br/>
&nbsp;Everyone is permitted to copy and distribute verbatim copies of this<br/>
&nbsp;license, but changing it is not allowed.  You can also use this wording to<br/>
&nbsp;make the terms for other programs.<br/>
<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;The license agreements of most software companies keep you at the mercy of<br/>
those companies.  By contrast, our general public license is intended to give<br/>
everyone the right to share NetHack.  To make sure that you get the rights we<br/>
want you to have, we need to make restrictions that forbid anyone to deny you<br/>
these rights or to ask you to surrender the rights.  Hence this license<br/>
agreement.<br/>
<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;Specifically, we want to make sure that you have the right to give away<br/>
copies of NetHack, that you receive source code or else can get it if you<br/>
want it, that you can change NetHack or use pieces of it in new free<br/>
programs, and that you know you can do these things.<br/>
<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;To make sure that everyone has such rights, we have to forbid you to<br/>
deprive anyone else of these rights.  For example, if you distribute copies<br/>
of NetHack, you must give the recipients all the rights that you have.  You<br/>
must make sure that they, too, receive or can get the source code.  And you<br/>
must tell them their rights.<br/>
<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;Also, for our own protection, we must make certain that everyone finds out<br/>
that there is no warranty for NetHack.  If NetHack is modified by someone<br/>
else and passed on, we want its recipients to know that what they have is<br/>
not what we distributed.<br/>
<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;Therefore we (Mike Stephenson and other holders of NetHack copyrights) make<br/>
the following terms which say what you must do to be allowed to distribute or<br/>
change NetHack.<br/>
<br/>
<br/>
COPYING POLICIES<br/>
<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;1. You may copy and distribute verbatim copies of NetHack source code as<br/>
you receive it, in any medium, provided that you keep intact the notices on<br/>
all files that refer to copyrights, to this License Agreement, and to the<br/>
absence of any warranty; and give any other recipients of the NetHack<br/>
program a copy of this License Agreement along with the program.<br/>
<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;2. You may modify your copy or copies of NetHack or any portion of it, and<br/>
copy and distribute such modifications under the terms of Paragraph 1 above<br/>
(including distributing this License Agreement), provided that you also do the<br/>
following:<br/>
<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;a) cause the modified files to carry prominent notices stating that you<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;changed the files and the date of any change; and<br/>
<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;b) cause the whole of any work that you distribute or publish, that in<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;whole or in part contains or is a derivative of NetHack or any part<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;thereof, to be licensed at no charge to all third parties on terms<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;identical to those contained in this License Agreement (except that you<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;may choose to grant more extensive warranty protection to some or all<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;third parties, at your option)<br/>
<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;c) You may charge a distribution fee for the physical act of<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;transferring a copy, and you may at your option offer warranty protection<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;in exchange for a fee.<br/>
<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;3. You may copy and distribute NetHack (or a portion or derivative of it,<br/>
under Paragraph 2) in object code or executable form under the terms of<br/>
Paragraphs 1 and 2 above provided that you also do one of the following:<br/>
<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;a) accompany it with the complete machine-readable source code, which<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;must be distributed under the terms of Paragraphs 1 and 2 above; or,<br/>
<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;b) accompany it with full information as to how to obtain the complete<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;machine-readable source code from an appropriate archive site.  (This<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;alternative is allowed only for noncommercial distribution.)<br/>
<br/>
For these purposes, complete source code means either the full source<br/>
distribution as originally released over Usenet or updated copies of the<br/>
files in this distribution used to create the object code or executable.<br/>
<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;4. You may not copy, sublicense, distribute or transfer NetHack except as<br/>
expressly provided under this License Agreement.  Any attempt otherwise to<br/>
copy, sublicense, distribute or transfer NetHack is void and your rights to<br/>
use the program under this License agreement shall be automatically<br/>
terminated.  However, parties who have received computer software programs<br/>
from you with this License Agreement will not have their licenses terminated<br/>
so long as such parties remain in full compliance.<br/>
<br/>
<br/>
Stated plainly:  You are permitted to modify NetHack, or otherwise use parts<br/>
of NetHack, provided that you comply with the conditions specified above;<br/>
in particular, your modified NetHack or program containing parts of NetHack<br/>
must remain freely available as provided in this License Agreement.  In<br/>
other words, go ahead and share NetHack, but don\'t try to stop anyone else<br/>
from sharing it farther.
]]>
	</string>
	<string
		name="instructions">
<![CDATA[
<h1>The NetHack Android Port Manual</h1>

<p><small>This manual is displayed automatically once. If you need it later it can be found in the settings.</small></p>

<br/>
<h3>The basics</h3> 
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;Simply tap the screen to move one step in the desired direction.
Long-press to move until you run into something.
 
</p>

<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;Tap the character to interact with what\'s on the floor. Move up/down stairs, pick up objects, loot chests, etc.</p>

<p>
&nbsp;&nbsp;Pan and zoom works in the usual way with the drag and pinch gestures. If your phone is equipped with a d-pad
or trackball you can pan by pressing a direction key or rotating the trackball, while holding down
the center button. You can also zoom with the volume buttons.
</p>
	 
<p>
&nbsp;&nbsp;Pan the map and tap on a position to Travel to it (see the
<font color="lime"><em>_</em></font> command in the NetHack
help). This can be disabled with the <font color="aqua"><em>Travel after pan</em></font> option. <br/>
</p>

<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;Long-press an inventory item to specify an amount, when for instance dropping (<font color="lime"><em>d</em></font>) something.</p>

<br/>
<h3>The command panel</h3> 
<p>
&nbsp;&nbsp;The command panel is the scrollable row of buttons at the bottom of the screen.
When you click a button the game will do whatever is written on it, as though you typed
each character one after another: 
</p>

<p>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<font color="lime"><em>i</em></font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;view inventory<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<font color="lime"><em>20s</em></font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;search 20 times
</p>
		  
<p>
&nbsp;&nbsp;The sequence <font color="lime"><em>...</em></font> is treated as a special command to open the soft
keyboard.
</p>

<p>
&nbsp;&nbsp;Long-press on any button to change it, remove it, or add a new one to the left of it.
</p>
	 
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;Control commands are entered with <font color="lime"><em>^</em></font> followed by a letter:</p>
	  
<p>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<font color="lime"><em>^D</em></font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;kick a door<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<font color="lime"><em>^T</em></font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;teleport
</p>
	    
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;Meta commands are entered with <font color="lime"><em>M-</em></font> followed by a letter:</p>
	
<p>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<font color="lime"><em>M-j</em></font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;jump<br/>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<font color="lime"><em>M-2</em></font>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;two-weapon
</p>
	    
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;If you don\'t want to see the panel you can hide it in the settings.</p>


<br/>
<h3>The soft keyboard</h3>
<p>
&nbsp;&nbsp;Press <font color="lime"><em>...</em></font> to open the soft keyboard. Press back to close it again.
When the soft keyboard is opened you can play NetHack almost as you would on a regular terminal.
If you prefer to play with the keyboard you might want to turn the <font color="aqua"><em>Automenu</em></font> option off.
</p>

<br/>
<h3>The volume keys</h3>
<p>
&nbsp;&nbsp;The volume keys can be mapped to a number of different actions. <font color="aqua"><em>Zoom in</em></font>, <font color="aqua"><em>Zoom out</em></font>, <font color="aqua"><em>Toggle keyboard</em></font>,
 <font color="aqua"><em>Ctrl</em></font>, and <font color="aqua"><em>Meta</em></font>.
</p>
 
<p>
&nbsp;&nbsp;Press <font color="aqua"><em>Toggle keyboard</em></font> to open or close the soft keyboard.
Keep holding the volume key when you open the keyboard to close it again when you release the key.
</p>

<p>
&nbsp;&nbsp;Use <font color="aqua"><em>Ctrl</em></font> and <font color="aqua"><em>Meta</em></font> to send control and meta commands with a physical keyboard.
The soft keyboard will be opened if your phone doesn\'t have a physical one.   
</p>

<br/>
<small>
Please visit www.nethack.org or nethackwiki.com for more information, or press
<font color="lime"><em>?</em></font> in the game for a help menu.
</small>

<br/>
<h4><br/>Happy hacking!</h4>
]]>
	</string>
    <string name="HearseDescription">Hearse enables you to share Bones files from your dead characters with other Nethack players over the Internet. You will also encounter theirs as you play.</string>
    <string name="HearseDeleteBonesDesc">By default, Hearse deletes your bones after uploading.</string>
    <string name="HearseIDDescription">Hearse ID (This is generated the first time you send data to Hearse. You can copy it to keep the same identity on multiple machines.)</string>
</resources>
